בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is נב Nun Bet 52.
We pick up in the middle of נא עמוד ב Nun Aleph
Amud Bet and we're in the middle of figuring, of unpacking this
whole ברייתא braita that deals with how a בת כהן, bat kohen,
a daughter of a כהן kohen who commits adultery and how she
has a special punishment the Torah metes out for her שריפה srefah
and what that tells us about the ranking of the different executions
of the court, but what we've been doing now is really just
looking into the parameters of that case itself. Who are we talking
about? Is she נשואה, nesuah, is she ארוסה, arusah, the different types
of debates about that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara picks up
with the following:
it says
מה רבי ישמעאל, Mah Rabbi Yishmael, it's like if you look in
the left-hand margin between the גמרא Gemara and רש"י Rashi it says
like יכ"ה, Yod Chaf Hey, it's right across from that, it's about
20 lines down, okay? מה רבי ישמעאל, Mah Rabbi Yishmael, now what
is the position of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that we referenced earlier?
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, oh, I think I erased it from my
other שיעור, shiur, but anyway רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that the
שריפה srefah is only for the case of the נערה המאורסה, na'ara
ham'urasa, of when she's ארוסה arusah and that if she's נשואה nesuah
she gets חנק chenek like a normal בת ישראל. bas Yisrael. So
where is it רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? Or, you know, תניא בברייתא,
Tanya b'braita, ובת כהן כי תחל לזנות, U'vas kohen ki techel liznot,
בנערה המאורסה הכתוב מדבר. b'na'ara ham'urasa hakatuve medaber.
So
again, to remind you here, let's,
I don't know what we're going to do, I need this board
for too many different classes at once, but anyway, okay, so the
Torah says that by a normal case of a בת ישראל, bas
Yisrael,
okay, for נשואה nesuah
it's חנק chenek
and for ארוסה arusah
it is סקילה. skila.
Okay, and then by a בת כהן bat kohen it says שריפה.
srefah. So the question is who gets שריפה? srefah? And part of
that is a question of whether
you consider שריפה srefah to be more strict than סקילה skila because
you don't want to give a בת כהן bat kohen a less
strict punishment. Okay, so one approach was that both of these get
שריפה srefah and שריפה srefah is more חמור chamur than סקילה. skila.
The חכמים's Chachamim approach was that נשואה nesuah gets שריפה srefah because
that's more weighty than חנק, chenek, but the ארוסה arusah gets סקילה
skila because סקילה skila is the weightiest, okay? And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael is going to say no, שריפה srefah is the weightiest. So
the ארוסה arusah gets שריפה srefah because that's, here we see the
same way this is a weighty punishment this is a weighty one
but this is even weightier than סקילה. skila. But the נשואה, nesuah,
that's just going to remain the normal חנק. chenek. That's what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is going to say, that's different than what we've
seen until now. Alright, so, בנערה
המאורסה,
b'na'ara
ham'urasa, it's נערה מאורסה na'ara m'urasa which is not just an ארוסה,
arusah, by the way, נערה מאורסה, na'ara m'urasa, which is exactly this
case here. בנערה המאורסה הכתוב מדבר, b'na'ara ham'urasa hakatuve medaber, אתה אומר
בנערה המאורסה או אינו אלא אפילו נשואה? ata omer b'na'ara ham'urasa o
eino ela afilu nesuah? Maybe it's the נשואה nesuah that gets שריפה?
srefah? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, איש אשר ינאף את אשת רעהו מות
יומת הנואף והנואפת. Ish asher yinaf et eshet re'ehu mot yumat hano'ef
v'hano'efes. If a man commits adultery, he and the woman are put
to death and the standard put to death is חנק chenek without
it clarifying. הכל היו בכלל הנואף והנואפת. Hakol hayu bichlal hano'ef v'hano'efes.
Everybody was included in the adulterer and the
adulteress to get חנק. chenek. הוציא הכתוב בת ישראל בסקילה, Hotzi hakatuve
bas Yisrael b'skila, ארוסה ולא נשואה. arusah v'lo nesuah. So חנק chenek
is for everybody who commits adultery. Then here it makes an exception
and says a נערה מאורסה na'ara m'urasa gets a special case of
סקילה. skila. So when it makes an exception by a בת כהן
bat kohen to say שריפה, srefah, presumably it should be in an
analogous case or the same case that it's making the exception. חנק
chenek is the default, okay? נערה מאורסה Na'ara m'urasa is a special
weighty case of סקילה. skila. So if here there's a special weighty
punishment of שריפה, srefah, we should similarly assume it's by נערה מאורסה
na'ara m'urasa and everybody else remains by the default. כשם שהוציא הכתוב
בת ישראל בסקילה ארוסה ולא נשואה, K'shem shehotzi hakatuve bas Yisrael b'skila
arusah v'lo nesuah, so when it makes an exception for בת ישראל
bas Yisrael to get a weighty punishment of סקילה skila that's in
a case of ארוסה, arusah, אף כשם שהוציא הכתוב בת כהן לשריפה
ארוסה ולא נשואה, af k'shem shehotzi hakatuve bat kohen l'srefah arusah v'lo
nesuah, when it makes a special weighty punishment by a בת כהן
bat kohen to get שריפה, srefah, ארוסה ולא נשואה. arusah v'lo nesuah.
Okay, so that's a very reasonable point. This is a very weighty
death so the שריפה srefah is a very weighty death we'll limit
it to the נערה מאורסה. na'ara m'urasa. By the way, it's also
פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk which says
את אביה היא מחללת. Et aviha hi mechalelet. The focus on the
father suggests that she's still in the father's house, okay? But the
normal cases are going to be חנק chenek for the בת כהן
bat kohen as well. So that's a third position about who gets
שריפה. srefah. Now we continue.
זוממיו באו לכלל, Zomemav bo leichlal, now how about the point about
the men involved in this? The man who committed adultery with her,
עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, what punishment are they going to get? We've
already seen that they don't get שריפה. srefah. So they were in
the principle ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם, va'asitem lo ka'asher zamam, so now
the גמרא Gemara interrupts because it says בועלה מאי כאשר זמם? bo'alah
mai ka'asher zamam? What are you doing quoting the פסוק pasuk of
כאשר זמם ka'asher zamam which is an עדים זוממים edim zomemim פסוק?
pasuk? If you're talking about the man who had sex with her,
you should be, you know, that's not about עדים זוממים. edim zomemim.
So איכא דאמרי... ika d'amri... איכא אלא, ika ela, fine, we'll modify
the text. זומם בכלל מיתת בעלה, zomem bichlal misas ba'ala, we would
have assumed or the עדים זוממים edim zomemim are going to get
the punishment not that she would have gotten, but the punishment that
the man who committed adultery with her would have gotten, which would
have been חנק chenek and we've seen that before, משום שנאמר ועשיתם
לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו. mishum shene'emar va'asisem lo ka'asher zamam la'asos
leachiv. So it's לאחיו leachiv what they wanted to do to the
brother ולא לאחותו, velo laachoso, not what they wanted to do to
their sister. Okay so this also underscores the gender aspect. As we've
pointed out before, you can punish עדים זוממים edim zomemim for something
that they couldn't have done, a sin that they couldn't have performed,
maybe they're not כהנים kohanim or whoever whatever it might be, but
this particular thing which is only for a בת כהן, bas Kohen,
this is something that the man does not get who's involved in
it, and it's because he ומיחללה, u-mechalela, and it's also something that
the עדים זוממים edim zomemim don't get, they only get the punishment
that the man would have gotten which would have been חנק. chenek.
Okay, תניא רבי ישמעאל, tanya Rebbi Yishmael, that's רבי ישמעאל. Rebbi Yishmael.
So the זוממים zomemim and the בועל boel we've seen before, okay,
but the key here is that he limits שריפה sreifah to the
נערה מאורסה na'ara me'orasa case.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rebbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says:
אחת ארוסה ואחת נשואה יצאו לשריפה. achas arusa ve-achas nesua yatze'u le-sreifah.
Now רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says, no, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says
both get שריפה. sreifah. That was also the position if you remember,
this is the position of רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva is now the position of
I think it's רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, okay, and therefore רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva says שריפה sreifah is for everybody. It just says שריפה,
sreifah, so it's both נשואה nesua and, so this is here, this
is רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael,
okay, this is now רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, we've also seen that
that's the position of רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, not רבי שמעון, Rebbi
Shimon, is it רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? Am I right?
What?
Was it רבי, Rebbi, no, רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
no,
what,
was it who was it? Was it רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon?
Now I'm so confused, who was the, there's so many different opinions
here.
Yeah, רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, it was רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, okay,
that was the position of רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Okay fine, and
if people are just for keeping track, we're not going to go
back to it, but the חכמים hachamim who say that all of
these assume שריפה sreifah is worse because שריפה sreifah replaces סקילה, skilah,
the חכמים hachamim who say that סקילה skilah is worse, limit שריפה
sreifah to the נשואה nesua case and put סקילה skilah down here.
Okay, but anyway we're back, forget the חכמים, hachamim, we're going to
look at this. Everybody here says שריפה sreifah is worse. רבי ישמעאל
Rebbi Yishmael says we're just going to limit it to the ארוסה
arusa case, which is the cases which get weighty punishment, everybody else
is going to default חנק, chenek, and רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says
it applies to all cases of בת כהן, bas Kohen, anyway even
a נשואה. nesua.
Okay, and in a different opinion too, what's, רבה Rabba says that
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
falls like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon.
Yeah I don't want to worry about רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer right
now. Okay, רבי עקיבא אומר אחת ארוסה ואחת נשואה יצאו לשריפה. Rebbi
Akiva omer achas arusa ve-achas nesua yatze'u le-sreifah. They both get שריפה.
sreifah. יכול אפילו פנויה, yachol afilu pnuya,
now maybe כי היכי דפליגי, ki heichi de-paligi, we had this question
before, maybe it's even if she's not married. נאמר כאן אביה ונאמר
להלן אביה בנערה מאורסה, ne'emar kan aviah vene'emar le-halan aviah be-na'ara me'orasa,
her father, מה להלן זנות עם זיקת הבעל, ma le-halan zenus im
zikas ha-ba'al,
the same way by the נערה מאורסה na'ara me'orasa where it says
את בית אביה, es beis aviah, that's talking about that she's married,
she's a נערה מאורסה, na'ara me'orasa, אף כאן זנות עם זיקת הבעל.
af kan zenus im zikas ha-ba'al. So he uses אביה aviah to
tell you that she's married. Of course the simplest thing to use
אביה aviah for is like a רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael approach, just
to say it's limited to a case of מאורסה, me'orasa, מאורסה me'orasa
who's still in her father's house. So that's what רבי ישמעאל Rebbi
Yishmael is basically going to say back to רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva.
אמר לו רבי ישמעאל, amar lo Rebbi Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael
said back to him, אם מה להלן נערה וארוסה אף כאן נערה
וארוסה, im ma le-halan na'ara ve-arusa af kan na'ara ve-arusa, if you're
going to focus on the word אביה aviah then you should, to
tell you that she's married, you should come along to my side,
you should say that it's telling you really link it to נערה
מאורסה na'ara me'orasa and that she has to be a נערה מאורסה.
na'ara me'orasa. A, because that's the case you're learning from, נערה מאורסה,
na'ara me'orasa, and B, the word אביה aviah itself, I'm throwing this
in, suggests the idea of נערה מאורסה. na'ara me'orasa. So or at
least of
מאורסה. me'orasa. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo Rebbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva said back to him, ישמעאל אחי, Yishmael achi, ישמעאל Yishmael
my brother, ובת ובת אני דורש. u-vas u-vas ani doresh. It's the
fact it says ובת איש כהן. u-vas ish Kohen. If it just
said בת איש כהן bas ish Kohen I would have linked it
to the נערה מאורסה na'ara me'orasa where it says בית אביה beis
aviah and I would have said that she's a, that it's only
when a case of an ארוסה, arusa, but the extra ו, vav,
ובת, u-vas, tells me we're talking about all cases of a בת
כהן bas Kohen anyway, even a נשואה. nesua. אמר לו וכי מפני
שאתה דורש בת ובת נוציא זו לשריפה? amar lo ve-chi mipnei she-atah
doresh bas u-vas notzi zo le-sreifah? This is such a great line,
which is רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, as we know
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva דורש doresh every little letter, every little dot
on every יוד, yod, רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael is more
of the דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam,
that the תורה Torah talks like the way people talk, you don't
hyper interpret every little letter. So the beautiful distillation of that debate
is the Just because it says the extra vav ו *vav*, you're
going to burn this poor woman? You know? So, the pshat פשט
pshat *pshat* is, logically, if you compare it to this case, you
know, just conceptually by the analogy, this is the weightier punishment we
should assign the weightier punishment here. If you want to look at
the words, it both says, it both says beis avih בית אביה
*beis avih*. Logically beis avih בית אביה *beis avih* is a case
of an arusah ארוסה arusah, *arusah*, so sreifah שרפה sraifah *sreifah* should
be limited to this. Because of that little extra vav ו *vav*
u'vas ish kohein ובת איש כהן Kohen, *u'vas ish kohein* you're going
to take this woman and you're going to burn her? Okay, mipnei
shene'emar v'uvath מפני שנאמר ובת *mipnei shene'emar v'uvath*. Dibra Torah kilshon bnei
adam דיברה תורה Torah כלשון בני אדם Adam *dibra Torah kilshon bnei
adam*, that's the phrase for Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*. Anyway,
mipnei she'atah doreish v'uvath מפני שאתה דורש ובת *mipnei she'atah doreish v'uvath*,
notzisholi sreifah נוציא זו לשרפה *notzisholi sreifah*? Im mashma l'havi es hanesu'ah,
havi es hapnuya אם משמע להביא את הנשואה, הבא את הפנויה *im
mashma l'havi es hanesu'ah, havi es hapnuya*. If you want to sort
of sort of say that u'vath ובת *u'vath* is a general phrase
referring to any type of a woman, then it should also include
the unmarried woman. Ve'im mashma lehotzi es hapnuya ואם משמע להוציא את
הפנויה *ve'im mashma lehotzi es hapnuya*, and if because of the link
to beis avih בית אביה *beis avih* and whatever, you're going to
exclude an unmarried woman and you're going to limit her to a
case of like the naarah merusah נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah *naarah merusah*
case, hotzi es hanesu'ah הוציא את הנשואה *hotzi es hanesu'ah*, you should
be excluding the nesu'ah נשואה *nesu'ah*. So the logical comparisons if you
just like pshat פשט *pshat* of words, either you say bas ish
kohein בת איש כהן *bas ish kohein* is generic and she doesn't
have to be married, or you compare it to the naarah merusah
נערה מאורסה *naarah merusah* case and you say that she has to
be a naarah merusah נערה מאורסה *naarah merusah*. So those are the
two logical options. Your extra vav ו *vav* to make her get
sreifah שרפה sraifah *sreifah*, you know, I'm not going to do that
because of an extra vav ו *vav*. So Rabbi Ishmael, okay, so
the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*,
Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would answer back, so now the
Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is speaking up. Hani gezeirah shavah l'mautei pnuya
הני גזירה שוה למעוטי פנויה *hani gezeirah shavah l'mautei pnuya*. No, the
gezeirah shavah גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* of beis avih בית אביה *beis
avih* tells you to, tells you that we're not including a unmarried
woman. Ahanei bas u'vath אהני בת ובת *ahanei bas u'vath* and the
extra vav ו *vav* tells you l'rabbos es hanesu'ah לרבות את הנשואה
*l'rabbos es hanesu'ah* that we are not just limiting ourselves to an
arusah ארוסה arusah. *arusah*, we're including a nesu'ah נשואה *nesu'ah*. Fine, it
repeats back what Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says, but Rabbi
Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* is unconvinced. V'Rabbi Ishmael savar ורבי ישמעאל
סבר *v'Rabbi Ishmael savar*, and Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* is
of the opinion, mi d'ka amralei bas u'vath מדקאמר ליה בת ובת
*mi d'ka amralei bas u'vath*, sh'ma mina hadar bei m'gezeirah shavah שמע
מינה הדר ביה מגזירה שוה *sh'ma mina hadar bei m'gezeirah shavah*. Now
the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rather than saying that Rabbi Ishmael רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* has a deep disagreement with Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva*, for some reason the Bavli בבלי *Bavli* chooses to frame
it like it was a misunderstanding. Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*
thought that because Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* went to the
extra vav ו *vav*, he was ignoring the gezeirah shavah גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* and that's why and he was, you know, retracting the
gezeirah shavah גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and that's why he asked. But
it really wasn't that he thought he was retracting, it's really like
he was sort of saying, "You should retract. Make up your mind.
Either interpret it without the gezeirah shavah גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and
have it apply to all women, or focus on the gezeirah shavah
גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* or on the analogy and limit it to
a naarah merusah נערה מאורסה *naarah merusah*." Okay. Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Ishmael*, hai bas u'vath mai darish bei? האי בת ובת מאי
דריש ביה *hai bas u'vath mai darish bei*? You know, this is
just so
humorous, because the whole point of Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*
is don't give me a problem with the extra vav ו *vav*,
and oh okay but what does he do with the extra vav
ו *vav*? Now, you know, now partly, you know, the way the
Bavli בבלי *Bavli* is framing it is that the extra vav ו
*vav* isn't powerful enough to take us out of our fundamental comparison
to naarah merusah נערה מאורסה *naarah merusah* and to limit it to
a case of an arusah ארוסה arusah, *arusah*. But it's not like
he disagrees that you have to do something with the extra vav
ו *vav*. So what is he going to do with the extra
vav ו *vav*? Okay. Mibaei lei l'khide'tanya Avuha d'Shmuel bar Avin מבעי
ליה לכדתניא אבוה דשמואל בר אבין *mibaei lei l'khide'tanya Avuha d'Shmuel bar
Avin*, like what Avuha d'Shmuel bar Avin אבוה דשמואל בר אבין *Avuha
d'Shmuel bar Avin* taught: l'fi shematzinu she'chillek hakatuv b'zacharim bein tmimim l'ba'alei
mumim לפי שמצינו שחילק הכתוב בזכרים בין תמימים לבעלי מומים *l'fi shematzinu
she'chillek hakatuv b'zacharim bein tmimim l'ba'alei mumim*. We know when it comes
to male kohanim כהנים kohanim, *kohanim*, there's a difference between if they
have a blemish and they don't have a blemish, if they can
work in the Beis HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. Yakhol
nachlok bivnoseihem? יכול נחלוק בבנותיהם *yakhol nachlok bivnoseihem*? Maybe laws that apply
specifically to bas kohein בת כהן bas kohen *bas kohein*, maybe it
should only be a bas kohein בת כהן bas kohen, *bas kohein*
who is unblemished, which is such a bizarre idea because blemish only
matters for avodah עבודה *avodah* in the Beis HaMikdash בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. But again it's sort of like the Gemara גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* before, except it's even a weaker version of it, that
maybe if she's married to a mamzer ממזר *mamzer* or a non-kohein,
her kehunah's כהונה *kehunah* already somehow compromised, and therefore the punishment is
not sreifah שרפה sraifah *sreifah*. So there we actually saw a debate
about that if she's let's say married to a mamzer ממזר *mamzer*
or a challal חלל *challal*. But here to think that a blemish
would somehow matter and somehow already compromise her kehunah כהונה *kehunah* status
for a bas kohein בת כהן bas kohen *bas kohein* is a
funny hava amina הוה אמינא hava amina. *hava amina*. But anyway, let's
see what it says: Talmud lomar: bas u'vath תלמוד לומר בת ובת
*Talmud lomar: bas u'vath*. The extra vav ו *vav* tells you no,
doesn't matter, anybody who falls into this category, blemished or unblemished, that
obviously does not matter for this halachah הלכה halakha *halachah* about getting
sreifah שרפה sreifa. *sreifah*. V'Rabbi Akiva ורבי עקיבא *v'Rabbi Akiva*, and Rabbi
Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would learn it from v'heim makrivim v'hayu
kodesh והם מקריבים והיו קדש *v'heim makrivim v'hayu kodesh*. It says they
are bringing, they shall be holy by the kohanim כהנים kohanim, *kohanim*,
so therefore it's this idea of only the ones, only the ve'heim
והם *ve'heim*, right? Oh actually I'm sorry, no, it's v'hayu kodesh והיו
קדש *v'hayu kodesh*. It's interesting, even heim makrivim והם מקריבים *heim makrivim*
seems like it's the one that can do the hakravah הקרבה *hakravah*,
right? V'hayu kodesh והיו קדש *v'hayu kodesh* is that they're all holy
whether they have the mum מום *mum* or don't have the mum
מום *mum*, there might be a limit from bringing a korban קרבן
*korban* but it's not a compromise in their kedushah קדושה kedusha. *kedushah*.
I mean the real place you see this by the male kohanim
כהנים *kohanim* is the fact that they eat the korbanos קרבנות korbanos.
*korbanos*, right? So the fact that they can eat the korbanos קרבנות
*korbanos* that are limited to the male kohanim כהנים *kohanim* in the
Beis HaMikdash בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, right, and nevertheless shows
that the mum מום *mum* issue is just an issue of the
avodah עבודה *avodah*, not of their kedushah קדושה *kedushah*. Okay. Nafka, Rabbi
Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*, Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* would
say back, "If me'hahi אם מההיא *im me'hahi*, if that was the
only basis, havah amina הוה אמינא *havah amina*..." הוה אמינא הני מילי
אינהו, that tells you the male כהנים, which is אבל בנתייהו לא,
aval binateihu lo, but maybe the female כהנים, maybe if they have
a blemish, of course the irony is, for them why would you
even think a blemish is relevant? Okay, but anyway, maybe that would
somehow compromise their קדושה. קא משמע לן. kamashma lan. That's a very
funny הוה אמינא. All right, but bottom line, Rabbi Ishmael limits שרפה
sreifa? to the most analogous case and Rabbi Akiva like Rabbi Shimon
applies שרפה sreifa to every case of a בת כהן Bas Kohen,
who is married. You had a question before, Michal? Okay,
Rabbi Ishmael. Now, Rabbi Ishmael, את אביה היא מחללת, es aviha hi
mechaleles, מאי דריש בה? mai darish bei? Since Rabbi Akiva from את
אביה es aviha learned to link it to נערה מאורסה by גזרה
שוה, gezeirah shavah, but Rabbi Ishmael does it more by analogy, not
by a word link. He says since the weightier punishment here by
a בת ישראל bas Yisrael is assigned to an ארוסה, we should
assume the weightier punishment of שרפה sreifa. is limited to an ארוסה.
It's analogy. He doesn't learn it from a word link of גזרה
שוה gezeirah shavah of את אביה. es aviha. So what does he
do with the words את אביה? es aviha? What does he learn
something special from that? Again, as I've been saying, את אביה es
aviha itself signals an ארוסה, but the גמרא Gemara hasn't said that.
So מאי דריש בה? mai darish bei? What does he do with
it? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibayei lei l'chad'tanya, like we taught in the
ברייתא. Baraita. את אביה היא מחללת. es aviha hi mechaleles.
What does it mean she is, you know,
desecrating her father, profaning her father? אם היו נוהגים בו קודש נוהגים
בו חול. im hayu nogim bo kodesh nogim bo chol. This is
not actually telling you just what the effect of her act is
naturally, but also how we as a community should react to her
action. If she goes ahead and does this, we now have to
show that we no longer treat her father as holy, that now
her actions reflect on her father
and we have to act towards her father appropriately. So if we
were treating her father with holiness, we should treat him in a
mundane fashion, you know, don't give him any special honor. נוהגים בו
כבוד, nogim bo kavod, if we used to treat him with honor,
נוהגים בו בזיון. nogim bo bizayon. We, you know, disparage him, we
go ahead and we're nasty to him in the marketplace and we
say bad rumors about him. I mean, I'm just making that up.
Obviously there's איסורים issurim about לשון הרע lashon hara and, you know,
and רכילות rechilut and all those types of things. So it's but
it's very funny like that there's this idea here of like public
shaming or at least stripping somebody of the honors because, you know,
we sort of see the actions of the child reflect on the
father. I mean, when the Torah describes it, it sort of describes
it that that's naturally how people will perceive it, right? It says,
you know, but here it's actually telling us that we're supposed to
act that way. אומרים, omrim,
you say, ארור שזו ילדו, arur shezo yaldu, ארור שזו גידלו, arur
shezo gildo, cursed is
the person that gave birth to this daughter, cursed is the man
that raised this daughter. ארור שיצא זו מחלציו, arur sheyatza zo mechalatzav,
cursed is the person from whose loins, you know, issued this daughter
who went ahead and acted this way. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav
Ashi, כמאן קרינן, k'man karinan, and just to show that some echo
of this remains, כמאן קרינן רשיעא בר רשיעא, k'man karinan rashia bar
rashia, ואפילו לרשיעא בר צדיקא? va'afilu l'rashia bar tzadika? Nowadays, if somebody
is like a wicked person, an evildoer, we call them, you know,
a wicked person, son of a wicked person, and we'll say that
even if their mother and father are righteous. We'll still call the
people a son of a wicked person. Who do we follow that?
כמאן? k'man? כהאי תנא k'hai tanna like Rabbi Meir. You actually go
ahead and you ascribe, you know, it's like לא יומתו אבות על
בנים, lo yumsu avos al banim, but here you're ascribing the sin,
at least you're faulting the parents and you're painting them all with
the
same brush and according to this, you're even calling the
parents רשעים resha'im if the children are רשעים. resha'im. So I look,
you know, I guess you could understand this that if you live
in such a society, you know, obviously it's going to put that
much heavier of a sense of burden and responsibility on the parents
to try to make sure that their kids, you know, grow up,
you know, and keep to the straight and narrow and live respectable
lives, right? So it'll certainly, you know, that will have some impact,
you know, I think on probably in a lot of cases, you
know, this real communal censure and this making sure that everybody, you
know, lives certain types of lives. On the other hand, it's really
very, very sad, you know. You raise your kids the best you
can and they go off and they're independent agents and they make
decisions for themselves and then, you know, to go ahead and to
be like publicly shamed like this, you know, to us I think
as, you know, as Westerners, it does not feel like this is
the type of society we want to be living in, that parents
are publicly shamed, you know. On the other hand, we do feel
that a lot of times, I think people
abnegate their responsibility in terms of raising of their kids. So, you
know, it's always about finding that right balance of like social pressure
to achieve the desired result without, you know, really suffering for something
that you're not to blame for.
But it does truly happen.
Yeah. Well, it happens naturally, but to be told that we're supposed
to be doing this, you
know, so I don't know and again every... So I don't know
and again everything is based on the time, but the
חרדי *Chareidi* community, that the kids don't want to be religious.
Right. It brings shame to the parents. Right.
Yeah, but in
some of those communities though if the kid also has some type
of a psychological issue or disability, it also brings shame to the
parents. So that's not this. That's a kid that's when something is
beyond somebody's
control. So I mean there are societies which there's a lot of
shame going around, right? And that's there's a lot of like secret
and hiding things and so on. That's not here. At least it's
about things that are about choices that are being made and that
might to some degree actually reflect to some degree about the upbringing
that people have and
so
on.
Right. I understand.
Look, I understand. I think if we had to choose, I think
at least myself, our value is rather live in a society in
which there's not people are shaming
everybody, but the question is that is there a balance where there's
enough of a feeling of societal pressure that people are making better
choices? That's always the question. Like peer pressure can be a good
thing if in the right proportions when it's pushing you to make
right choices rather than wrong choices and those types of things. So
yeah. Alright, I don't know, it's obviously something to be challenging idea.
It's a position of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, it's not what everybody
interprets the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Let's keep on going. זו מצות הנסקלין
*Zo mitzvat haniskalin*. So after laying out the ארבע מיתות arba misos.
*arba misos*, the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* ends and says what we've just
discussed until now is סקילה skila *skila*. מאי תנא דקתני זו מצות
הנסקלין *Mai tanna d'ktani zo mitzvat haniskalin*? What's the point of saying
זו מצות הנסקלין *zo mitzvat haniskalin* at the end of this משנה
mishnah. *Mishnah* of the ארבע מיתות arba misos *arba misos*? משום דתנא
נגמר הדין מוציאין אותו ליסקל *Mishum d'tana nigmar hadin motzin oto liskol*
because the previous פרק perek *perek* describes סקילה sekila, *skila*. It says
when the judgment was done, they took him out to stone him
and then it says בית הסקילה היתה גבוה שתי קומות *Beit haSkila
hayta gavoa shtei komos*, how high it was, the platform they pushed
him off from, and then it speaks about hanging him. ואיידי דקא
בעי למתנא מצות הנשרפין *V'aidie d'ka ba'ei l'mitna mitzat hanisrafin*, so now
we're going to go ahead and we're going to move from סקילה
*skila* to שריפה sereifa *sreifa*. We interrupted it with this list of
giving the hierarchy. So therefore, תני נמי זו מצות הנסקלין *tani nami
zo mitzvat haniskalin*. Really the זו מצות הנסקלין *zo mitzvat haniskalin* should
have preceded the elaboration of it. We're sort of going back and
reflecting backwards, but we're transitioning from סקילה *skila* to שריפה sreifa *sreifa*.
We introduced סקילה *skila*, so now we're sort of saying what we
talked about before was סקילה *skila*, now let's move on to שריפה
sreifa? *sreifa*. Of course the irony or the irony, the funny question
is that why did we not start with ארבע מיתות arba misos
נמסרו לבית דין *Arba Misos Nimseru l'Beit Din*? The logical thing would
have been to do there are four מיתות misos *misos* and now
we'll say זו מצות *zo mitzvat*... now here סקילה *skila*, then give
us סקילה *skila*, then say here שריפה sreifa. *sreifa* and give us
שריפה sreifa, *sreifa*. The way the משניות *Mishnayos* were arranged was it
says they decided the guy was חייב מיתה chayav mita. *chayiv misa*,
they took him out to do סקילה *skila*, describe the whole סקילה
*skila*. Then it said, oh by the way, I should mention there
are actually four types of מיתות בית דין misos beis din. *misos
Beit Din* and that was סקילה *skila*, now let's go on to
talk about שריפה sreifa, *sreifa*. So why did you first describe סקילה
*skila* and then put it in? The other funny thing about it
is that the impression you get reading those earlier משניות *Mishnayos* is
that the default is חנק chenek, *chenek*, right? It says the guy
was decided he was going to die, they took him out to
do סקילה *skila*. And then we find out that actually the default
is חנק chenek *chenek* and סקילה *skila*'s the weightiest. So why does
it like introduce, why does it just have that like move? Why
it starts with סקילה *skila* I get. If you want to talk
about the weightiness, you start with the weighty one and you work
down. But the fact that it didn't have the introduction and it
just said, once the guy was decided that the guy was liable
to the death penalty, they took him out to do סקילה *skila*,
makes it sound like סקילה *skila* is the default. So I really
don't know the answer about why this list of the four occurs
only after we described סקילה *skila* and we had that natural sort
of transition to סקילה *skila* as if that was the most natural
thing and then we interrupted the narrative with talking about here are
the four מיתות *misos*, so I don't really know the answer to
that.
Yeah. This may relate to the debate that comes up afterwards about
which is the weightiest...
Sure, but you're going to have that debate either way. Oh, they
wanted to put their opinion first. Could be. They wanted to sort
of make it clear, no, סקילה *skila* really is the weightiest just
so you know, right, maybe, maybe, yeah. Do we know how often
any of this happened?
No, we don't.
And we're going actually see a case in a coming משנה Mishnah.
*Mishnah* right here about an actual case, about how they executed somebody
and we know the whole case of שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben
Shetach, *Shimon ben Shatach* killed eighty witches at once. But how often
this really happened and did it really happen according to this thing?
A lot of scholars think that most of this is describing what
the system should look like and it's not really a historical record
of what was done. And we'll get in a minute I'll mention
something Sasha Stern has a whole book on this called I forget
what, I think it has the word punishment in it but it's
not Crime and Punishment. It's something else. Anyway, and there's a book
also in Israel by Aaron Shemesh and somebody else about the ארבע
מיתות arba misos. בית דין Beis Din, *Arba Misos Beit Din* about
like what are חז"ל *Chazal* trying to communicate by this whole system?
So I actually my plan over שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* is to do
a little חזרה *chazara* of those books so I'll tell you
but
I'll tell you... Probably they did execute people when they felt it
was necessary, you know, we know they did that even, you know,
in the Middle Ages, not because it was the formal הלכה, halakhic
but it was the community regulating itself. And certainly, often execution was
more rare, but often it was like, you know, corporal punishment, lashes,
other types of things, not that it followed the formal הלכות halachos
of this; it was just the way the community, you know, sort
of governed itself and dealt with, you know, oh, you
know, malfeasors. But anyway, but like how much did it follow this
whole process and the עדים eidim and then you run after to
retrieve it and, you know, all of that in exactly this way,
I don't know if there's any evidence about how much this actually
really happened. Let's take a look at the next משנה.
Mishnah, You needed a סנהדרין Sanhedrin in order to have all those
details.
Yes, in principle, in principle.
So why would they have had that kind of thing happening in
the Middle Ages where they have witnesses?
Because they because it was they did it, they didn't have to
the formal executions of בית דין, Beis Din, but sometimes as a
community, and now how they הלכה-ly halakhic justified it is interesting, but
you know, but they the governments, the non-Jewish governments gave them, you
know, limited autonomy to sort of govern themselves. So what do you
do about people that are, you know, really, you know, not just,
you know, not somebody who's מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, that's not the
person you're going to, you know, you're going to execute, but the
person who's like, let's say, a real physical threat to the community
or somebody, you know, what do you do with them, right? So
sometimes, not because of the formal הלכות halachos of the, you know,
of the punishments in the תורה Torah and the process of a
בית דין, Beis Din etc., just a discipline, you know, type of
a way, you know.
But would they still have used these details?
No. So that's my point, they did not. They did not. It
was sort of extrajudicial the way they handled it or extra-legal the
way they handled it. Look, the גמרא Gemara says בית דין מכין
ועונשין שלא מן הדין, Beis Din makin veonshin shelo min hadin, that
בית דין beis din. sometimes can choose to to institute punishments which
are not following these formal rules, you know, for the sake of,
you know, ultimately, in, you know, protecting the community and protecting the
תורה Torah. and so on. So to certain type of like, you
know, extra-legal rights. Okay. So anyway, let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishnah. מצוות הנשרפין, Mitzvos HaNisrafin, so now now that we've done
with סקילה and we introduced the hierarchy, let's move on to שרפה.
sreifa How do they do שרפה? sreifa היו משקעין אותו בזבל עד
ארכובותיו, hayu mashki'in oso bezevel ad arkovosav, they would put him into
in
in dung. Now that seems like it's done as a way of
disgracing him, but at least the way רש"י Rashi and, you know,
the מפרשים meforshim explain, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say it's for the
purpose of disgrace, it's just as a way of like holding him
steady. Again, I don't know why this was your only option. הארכובותיו,
arkovosav, ארכובות arkovos are what, your knees? What are the ארכובותיו? arkovosav?
How does it? It says knees. Knees, until his knees. Okay. ונותנים,
venosnim, I would imagine there's got to be a better way, but
okay. ונותנים סודר קשה לתוך הרכה, venosnim sudar kasha lesoch haraka, you
would put a hard like rope inside of a soft, you know,
like like
what's it called, not handkerchief, what's the word? Scarf. Scarf, thank you.
Inside of a soft scarf, you put like a rope inside of
a scarf. So the reason is you don't want, A, you don't
want to disfigure him and leave scar marks on his neck, you
know, and number two, the way ירושלמי Yerushalmi says it is, you
don't want to kill him because you're going to we're going to
see you're going to sort of pull on it enough to force
him to open his mouth, but you don't want to actually strangle
him in the process, okay? So therefore, you wrap a scarf around
a rope. וכורך על צוארו, vechorech al tzavaro, you wrap it around
his neck. זה מושך אצלו וזה מושך אצלו, ze moshech etzlo veze
moshech etzlo, each one pulls, you know, one person on each side
holding each end of the rope, pulling in opposite directions, עד שפותח
פיו, ad sheposayach pivo, it forces him to open his mouth. ומדליק
את הפתילה, umadlik es hapesila, you light the literally the wick, we'll
see what that is, וזורקה לתוך פיו, vezorka lesoch pivo, and you
throw it into his mouth, ויורדת לתוך מעיו, veyoredes lesoch me'av, and
it goes into his innards, into his stomach, וחומרת את בני מעיו,
vechomeres es bnei me'av, and it and it burns his insides. So
you basically שרפה sreifa is not by burning the outside of his
body, but by pouring something hot down his throat and that destroys
his inner his insides, burns his insides. רבי יהודה אומר אף הוא
מת בידם, Rabbi Yehuda omer af hu mes beyadam, if you do
this thing with the scarf, you're going to wind up strangling him
with the scarf and that will be חנק, we'll see that's exactly
what חנק is, and it won't be שרפה. לא היו מקיימין בו
מצוות שרפה, lo hayu mekaymin bo mitzvas sreifa, and then they wouldn't
fulfill the מצוות שרפה. mitzvas sreifa. אלא ela what they would do
is, פותח את פיו בצבת, posayach es pivo betzavas, they would use
actually בצבת, betzavas, thank you. Oh, צוות tzvet is like a staff
of a camp, right? בצבת, betzavas, right? Okay. פותח את פיו בצבת,
posayach es pivo betzavas, you would use a what's it called a
tongs, thank you, to like open up his mouth, you'd force his
mouth open with tongs, שלא בטובתו, shelo betovaso, even with him resisting,
okay, because then you'd have to really like, you know, again, if
you do the rope, he'd just be it'll be a natural response,
you know, but here he's going to be fighting against you, but
you force his mouth open with these tongs. ומדליק את הפתילה u'madlik
es haptilah and same thing, you light this wick, וזורקה לתוך פיו,
v'zorko l'toch piv, you throw it into his mouth, ויורדת לתוך מעיו
וחורכת את בני מעיו.
v'yoredes l'toch me'av v'chores es
b'nei mei'av. Okay, same point, except that's how you get his mouth
open. אמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק, Amar Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok, מעשה
בבת כהן אחת שזינתה, ma'aseh b'vas kohen achas she'zinasa, I actually saw,
and here we, this is the case we've been dealing with until
now, the בת כהן, bas kohen the paradigm שרפה case. I saw
that case of a בת כהן who committed adultery, והקיפוה חבילי זמורות
v'hekifuha chavilei zmoros and they did exactly what you would have thought
שרפה was, they wrapped her with bundles of, like, twigs, ושרפוה, u'serafuha,
and they burned her. So they literally burned her body, you know,
threw her into the funeral, into the pyre. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
they said to him, מפני שלא היה בית דין של אותה שעה
בקי, mipnei she'lo hayah beis din shel osah sha'ah baki, they didn't
know what they were doing, that בית דין. beis din Okay, that's
not the halachic way of doing it. So here's a great contrast
of what they actually did historically and what the Rabbis said should
have been done, and their response is, that might have been what
they did, but they didn't do it the right way. Okay. Now,
מהי פתילה, mai ptilah, what is this wick that you throw into
the mouth? So אמר רב מתנה, Amar Rav Masna, פתילה של אבר,
ptilah shel avar, it is lead. So it's not, רש״י Rashi says
it doesn't mean you light it, how do you light lead? So
רש״י Rashi says what it means is like you melt it. You
take it as, then it's not actually a wick, I mean I
guess you could start with a little piece of lead, but then
you melt it and then you pour molten lead down the throat.
הירושלמי ha'Yerushalmi has two other possibilities. It also says the possibility of
some mixture of lead and tin, and then it also says נפט,
neft, which is like, like it said, like a type of like
oil, right? What's naphtha? Isn't naphtha like some type of
petroleum? Naphtha, it's oil, right? Yeah. So it's some type of like
lit oil down the throat or heated
oil. I mean, oh God, that's got to be super painful. I
mean, less painful I assume than the external burning of the body,
but still got to be super painful. Okay, מנא לן, mina lan,
how do you know this from, how do you know that forget
the metal used, you use whatever you use, but how do you
know the way you do שרפה is by burning the insides of
the body rather than the
outside? So אתיא שרפה שרפה מעדת קרח. atya sreifa sreifa me'adas Korach.
You learn it from
קרח. Korach. מה להלן שרפת נשמה וגוף קיים אף כאן שרפת נשמה
וגוף קיים. mah le'halan sreifas neshamah v'guf kayam af kan sreifas neshamah
v'guf kayam. There it says that they were, you know, burnt, אנשים
שרופים, anashim srufim, and there we know that it was only the
inner body and the outer body remained, remained alive, it was just
the fire went inside them. How we know that, we'll see in
a minute. Okay, but that's the first
position. רבי אליעזר אומר אתיא שרפה שרפה מבני אהרן. Rabbi Eliezer omer
atya sreifa sreifa mi'bnei Aharon. No, it's בני אהרן bnei Aharon that
they were burnt, and that's only their insides were burnt, not their
outside. מה להלן שרפת נשמה וגוף קיים אף כאן שרפת נשמה וגוף
קיים. mah le'halan sreifas neshamah v'guf kayam af kan sreifas neshamah v'guf
kayam. Okay, so they both say that there's models of this in
the תורה. Torah. Of course, it's not clear for either of these
in the תורה. Torah So the גמרא Gemara says, now, מאן דייליף
מעדת קרח מנא ליה? man d'yalif me'adas Korach mina lei? Now, how
do you get this from קרח? Korach? How do you know that's
what happened? דכתיב, d'chesiv, את מחתות החטאים האלה בנפשותם, es machtos hachata'im
ha'eleh b'nafshosam, those who sinned with their souls. So it says, שנשמתם
נשרפה. she'nishmasam nisrefah. So it's taking the sin of the soul to
the punishment of the soul. Also, בנפשותם b'nafshosam just means themselves, right?
It doesn't have to mean נפש nefesh like the, like the soul
as opposed to the body, but it's reading the word נפש nefesh
as soul versus body, and it's saying that they paid with their
soul. Okay, so שנשמתם נשרפה וגוף קיים, she'nishmasam nisrefah v'guf kayam, that
their souls were burnt but their body remained intact. ואידך, v'idach, what
would the one who does not think קרח Korach is a model
say back? ההיא שרפה ממש. hahi sreifa mamash. No, no, no, no,
their bodies were literally burnt. ומה בנפשותם, u'mah b'nafshosam, so what does
it mean they sinned with their soul? שנתחייבו שרפה על עסקי נפשותם,
she'nischayvu sreifa al iskei nafshosam,
that the reason that they were liable was because of what they
did with their soul, and here what it's doing I believe is
the play on the words of נפש. nefesh. נפש nefesh can mean,
I mean, נפש nefesh can mean yourself, נפש nefesh could mean your
sort of soul in this soul-body dualism, but it could also mean,
you know, your appetitive part of yourself, like when it says
ביום כיפור, b'Yom Kippur, what is it? ועניתם את נפשותיכם, v'inisem es
nafshoseichem, so you should afflict your souls, which we say means don't
eat or drink or whatever. So people point out that in other
Semitic languages, the root נפש nefesh refers to the appetitive part of
yourself. You know, in some languages it even means your throat. Okay,
so which is interesting here because it's going down the throat. So
anyway, it's saying they sinned with their appetite. How did they sin
with their appetite? Let's take a look. שנשמתם, she'nishmasam, where is it?
שנתחייבו שרפה על עסקי נפשותם, she'nischayvu sreifa al iskei nafshosam, כדריש לקיש.
k'd'Reish Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש, d'amar Reish Lakish, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chesiv,
what's meant by the verse? בחנפי לעגי מעוג, b'chanfei la'agei ma'og, by
the flattery of the, of the, of the pouring of food, of
the, you know, of the serving of food, חרק עלי שנימו, charak
alai shinemo, their, you know, the teeth have, like, sharpened against him.
So what does that mean? So בשביל חנופה שהחניפו לקרח על עסקי
לגימה, bishvil chanufah she'hechanifu l'Korach al iskei legimah, because of, now here
it sounds like they're flattering קרח, Korach, but רש״י Rashi says it
was that קרח Korach was flattering them. קרח Korach flattered his followers
because he gave them a nice feast, you know, he honored them,
and then the context of feeding them and honoring them and giving
them this feast, he seduced them, you know, and he paid them
all these compliments and then he convinced them to come and to
be on his side. So because of that flattering that he did
על עסקי לגימא Al iskei legima on issues of like food and
eating, right? חרק עליו שר של גיהנום שיניו. Chireka alav sar shel
Gehenom shinav. So that allowed the you know the the the angel
of Gehenom to sharpen his teeth against them, right? That's sort of,
you know, that sort of ascribed them to hell that they were
allowed themselves to be seduced by Korach and flattered, you know, in
his meal and so on.
לגימא Legima like like whatever, alcoholic
drink?
Yeah, well, I don't we're not actually saying that this is the
basis for שריפה sreifa but that's an interesting point as well. The
throat and the drink and so on. I didn't think לגימא legima
were, you might be right, I didn't think I didn't know if
לגימא legima here was limited specifically to drinks but as opposed to
just in general like the eating or the serving of food but
regardless. Right, the point is is that their sin of their souls
means of their appetitive desires they allowed themselves to be seduced by
the meals and the feasts of Korach and that ultimately is what
led them astray. Okay, but it's not to say that their souls
were burnt and their body remained alive. So that's the debate around
Korach, how you interpret the word נפשותם. nafshotam. ומאן דיליף מבני אהרן
Uman deyalif mibnei Aharon
if you're learning from בני אהרן, bnei Aharon, מנליה minalei where do
you know it? דכתיב dechtiv וימותו לפני השם vayamutu lifnei Hashem they
die before God, this is Nadav and Avihu, כעין מיתה ke'ein mita
like death. So death is the body the soul departs and the
body remains. ואידך Ve'idach
what was the other one say back? הוא שריפה ממש Hu sereifa
mamash no, no, no, they literally their bodies were burnt. הוא. Hu.
ומאי דכתיב וימותו Umai dechtiv vayamutu so why does it say they
died, which sounds like it was a type of a death? דאתחילו
בהו מגואי De'itchilu behu migavai cause
the true, the fire started on the inside like death, it started
on the inside, but in the end it consumed their body as
well. It didn't leave their body intact. So they agree that it
was like death in that it started on the inside, but one
says it left the body intact and the other says it consumed
the body. כעין מיתה. Ke'ein mita. Okay, דתניא detanya like we learned
in a ברייתא baraita אבא יוסי בן דוסאי אומר Abba Yose ben
Dosai omer שני חוטים של אש יצאו מבית קדש הקדשים shnei chutin
shel esh yatz'u mibeit kodesh hakodashim two like strands of fire of
like the idea of the strand of metal that's poured down the
throat, right? Two strands of fire left out of the Holy of
Holies. ונחלקו לארבע Venechleku le'arba and
they divided into four. ונכנסו שנים בחוטמו של זה venichnasu shnayim bechotamo
shel zeh
two went into the one of their nostrils ושנים בחוטמו של זה
ushnayim bechotamo shel zeh and the other into the other's nostrils ושרפו
אותם vesarfu otam and it burnt them. Okay, now that sort of
shows that it started on the inside, I guess because it uses
the word שרפו sarfu burnt them, it shows that in the end
the fire entered into their body but burnt their whole body so
it did not leave their body intact. So everybody agrees it started
on the inside, did it leave their body intact? I also don't
know why it's described as two strands that broke into four. Why
not say it's one strand that broke into four or one, you
know, I mean I guess because there are two different people they
each were חייב מיתה. chayav misa Anyway, it's an interesting way of
describing it. Okay, והכתיב ותאכל אותם Vehatichiv vetochal otam it says it
ate them and אותם otam seems to be limiting, meaning meaning somehow
being read as their souls and not their
body. No, אותם ולא בגדיהם otam velo bigdeihem them and it didn't
consume their garments. Actually תוספות Tosafot points out because even the פסוק
pasuk says וישאום בכתנתם vayisa'um bechutnotam it says that they removed them
with their you know in their cloaks. So clearly their garments remained.
Okay, but actually the very fact that the verse says it they
transferred them, removed them, sounds like their body was still there. So
how do you explain it if it says that their body was
burnt? So could be their body was charred, it wasn't like it
turned to ash, right? It could be totally charred and still there.
תוספות Tosafot also there's an idea that the people who transferred them
became טמא מת. tamei meit. How are you טמא מת tamei meit
if all you have left is ash? So תוספות Tosafot says according
to the one that their body was burnt maybe at least the
the skeleton remained. And that's what they removed, they removed their skeletons
and that's why they were טמא מת tamei meit and so
on. Okay, but certainly the פסוק pasuk. וישאום vayisa'um sounds like their
body is there, which gives some support to the idea that their
body was intact. Okay, so anyway it says like this, so those
are our two
models. ונילף מפרים הנשרפים Veneilef miparin hanisrafin now why learn from Korach
or Nadav and Avihu, why not learn from the cows that if
you bring a certain cow you know a חטאת chatat an inner
חטאת chatat into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash you burn the animal
and you burn the body, you put it on a you put
it on a pile of on a fire on a on a,
you know, so why not do the same thing
here? ונילף מפרים הנשרפים Veneilef miparin hanisrafin מה להלן שריפה ממש אף
כאן שריפה ממש. ma lehalan sereifa mamash af kan sereifa mamash. No,
מסתברא מאדם הוה ליה למילף Mistabra me'adam hava lei lemeilaf it's better
learn out from one of these cases of Korach or Nadav and
Avihu rather than to learn out from a cow. Okay, שכן sheken
and here are the points of similarity אדם both cases are about
a person dying or being killed, חוטא Chotei they're both sinners Korach,
Nadav and Avihu, and the person we're executing. נשמה, neshama, in both
cases where it's like
they've done, what does Rashi say נשמה neshama here mean? One minute.
One minute.
Oh,
oh, the act of burning is the act of killing them. By
the case of the cows, they were already slaughtered. So and here
the act of burning is the act of killing them. פיגול pigul
and the idea of פיגול pigul is irrelevant because they weren't קרבנות.
So those are a lot of similarities and we'd rather learn from
them. אדרבה aderaba the opposite: מפרה ומשריפה הוה ליה למילף, mipara umishreifa
hava lei lemilaf,
let's learn execution from the burning of the cows, שכן shekein מכשיר,
machshir, number one is both of them is doing a מצוה. mitzvah.
There's a מצוה mitzvah to burn the cows and there's a מצוה
mitzvah for בית דין Beis Din to execute, as opposed to the
case of קרח Korach and בני אהרן, b'nei Aharon, which it was
God who was doing it. And לדורות, ledoros, both of these are
מצוות mitzvos that are given for future generations. It wasn't just a
one-time historical event. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הנך נפישי, haneich
nefishi, nevertheless, there are greater points of comparison between the humans and
the humans and we're going to use those as the model. Okay,
so we have the model either קרח Korach or בני אהרן. b'nei
Aharon. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאן דייליף מעדת
קרח מאי טעמא לא יליף מאהרן? man de'yalif me'adas Korach mai ta'ama
lo yalif me'Aharon? So we said the debate about whether קרח Korach
was, the body was intact or not, was how you read the
word נפשותם. nafshotam. But what's the, why not by בני אהרן, b'nei
Aharon, why not use that as your basis? Okay, 'cause why not,
if as long as you're conceding that the word מיתה misa means
it's like a death, why not say it's fully like a death
and the body remains intact? So ההוא שריפה ממש הוה. hahu sreifa
mamash hava. The גמרא Gemara says, I'm sorry, did I skip? No,
מאי טעמא לא יליף ההוא שריפה ממש הוה, mai ta'ama lo yalif
hahu sreifa mamash hava, so it's just sort of repeating I think
what it said before. It doesn't say why it doesn't learn it
otherwise. No, it says that that was literally the bodies were burned.
וניליף מיניה. veneilif minei. Now here we get to the question which
is: if one side says I'm learning from בני אהרן, b'nei Aharon,
there the body was intact, but בני קרח b'nei Korach they were
literally burned. And the other says no, the opposite, בני קרח b'nei
Korach was the body was intact, בני אהרן b'nei Aharon were literally
burned. So the question is fine, each of you has two models
to choose from, okay, why did you choose the model of the
body intact, why not choose the other model which is the body
was burned? Okay, so you're both saying that one of those cases
the body is intact and one it was burned. Why did you
choose the version, the one to learn how to do the execution
of the court from the case of when the body was intact?
וניליף מיניה, veneilif minei, why not learn from the case where the
body was burned? So אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר
קרא, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha amar kra, the verse
says ואהבת לרעך כמוך, ve'ahavta lerei'acha kamocha, ברור לו מיתה יפה. beror
lo misa yafa. No, if we have to choose between the external
burning of the body and this pouring of the lead, I mean
one is a much more, there's one that's much more preferable. I
mean one obviously destroys the body and it's disfiguring to the body
and obviously also it's, I gotta imagine, it's much much more painful,
right? So we're going to pick the better of the two. וכי
מאחר דאיכא דרב נחמן, vechi mei'achar de'ika de'Rav Nachman, now
once we have this principle of pick the better one, גזירה שוה
למה לי, gezeira shava lama li, why did we even need the
models? Why don't we just say that's what שריפה is, the nicer
שריפה? No, אי לאו גזירה שוה, ei lav gezeira shava, had we
not had this link, had this model, הוה אמינא שריפת נשמה וגוף
קיים לאו שריפה היא כלל, hava amina sreifas neshama veguf kayam lav
sreifa hi klal, which is what I would have said. I said
come on, that's not פשט in the פסוק. pasuk The פסוק pasuk
says burn the person. How do you think it means just pour
lead down them? So if we, so we need to prove that
it's a viable option. Okay, so ואי משום ואהבת לרעך כמוך, ve'ei
mishum ve'ahavta lerei'acha kamocha, and if we had just had ואהבת לרעך
כמוך, ve'ahavta lerei'acha kamocha, we would have thought we have to do
a burning of the body and we would have thought נפיש חבילי
זמורות כי היכי דלישתריף לעגל. nefish chavilei zemoros ki heichi de'lishtareif le'agal.
I would have said fine, make it a very very big fire
so the person would burn as fast as possible. I would have
had ways to do ואהבת לרעך כמוך ve'ahavta lerei'acha kamocha within the
classic just burning of the body. But I wouldn't have thought that
just pouring lead down a throat would have been an option. קא
משמלן, ka mashma lan, so the verse teaches me that also constitutes
שריפה. Once I know that that constitutes שריפה, then I will pick
that option because that is the better one. But if I did
not know that that constituted שריפה, I would have been limited to
the literal understanding of שריפה and I would have had to just
try to have made it as quick and as least excruciatingly painful
as possible. I wasn't going to say painless as possible. Okay, so
anyway, it's the combination of the two. ואהבת לרעך כמוך ve'ahavta lerei'acha
kamocha always operates, but it operates within the range of options that
I have. And I needed the model of בני אהרן b'nei Aharon
or קרח Korach to tell me that this was an option. Now
I want to tell you one brief issue about, I mentioned this
issue of these two books, Aaron Shemesh and Dvora Steinmetz about the
ארבע מיתות.
So
I don't remember all the details and Dvora Steinmetz does this brilliant
type of a chart of the ארבע מיתות and different ways in
which, whatever, I'll review it and I'll share it with you. But
one of the core debates is that Aaron Shemesh's book is basically
all about how
the sort of the body being created in the image of God,
right? We saw that before about the whole idea of hanging the
body, and therefore about how all of the ארבע מיתות are trying
to minimize the disfiguring of the body. That's his basic approach to
understanding a theme through these ארבע מיתות. You know, so you push
the person down by סקילה, you don't
stone. Right, you don't, you do all these things that are try
to minimize the disfiguring of the body. ספורנו Seforno says that that
is not the point, and she particularly emphasizes like here the fact
of the גמרא says כעין מיתה, ke'ein misa, like a death. And
what she sort of says is, it gets back to the larger
theme of how what entitles
anybody to use violence and actually execute somebody else? Like how can
you take somebody else's life? And one of the ways in which
you take somebody else's life is because of this whole concept that
אלקים, Elokim, you see yourself as like just executing God's judgment. So
if you see yourself as executing God's judgment, you want that form
of death that you are bringing about to be as close to
a divinely ordained death as possible. So if number one it mimics
the way God punished sinners by this fire coming out, but also
maybe even more to the point if it mimics the way that
people normally die, that the body is intact and the soul departs,
right? So it allows us to more be sort of
operating, sort of in the mode of like sort of bringing about
a divinely ordained death. So she really underscores the כעין מיתה ke'ein
misa part of this, as part of the whole message. So that's
like one key point of their debating like what's really going on
here in terms of the bigger issues. Yes.
Have we discussed previously that they drugged the person in some way?
That hasn't come up. We're going to sort of see that. Yeah,
we have not seen that yet.
Just how conscious the person is.
Yeah, well they have to be conscious enough to confess and so
on, but that's coming up. We haven't seen that yet. Okay. So
now that we mention נדב ואביהוא, Nadav v'Avihu, we have a nice
little digression about נדב ואביהוא. Nadav v'Avihu. וכבר היו משה ואהרן מהלכין
בדרך. v'chvar hayu Moshe v'Aharon mhalchin baderech. So now we're going to
give you the background of נדב ואביהוא. Nadav v'Avihu. So there was
משה Moshe and אהרן Aharon were taking a little walk. ונדב ואביהוא
מהלכין אחריהן, v'Nadav v'Avihu mhalchin achareihen, and נדב Nadav and אביהוא Avihu
were trailing
them. Okay, you had the seniors and then you had the juniors
behind them. וכל ישראל אחריהן, v'chol Yisrael achareihen, and then they were
followed by all of the Jewish people, all of Israel. So here
they were, they were in such an honored and lofty position. The
only people they were standing behind was משה Moshe and אהרן Aharon
and everybody else was behind them. Of course it wasn't good enough
for them. It's sort of like עדת קרח, Adas Korach, right? It's
never good enough. So אמר לו נדב לאביהוא, amar lo Nadav l'Avihu,
so נדב Nadav said to אביהוא, Avihu, אימתי ימותו שני זקנים הללו
ואני ואתה ננהיג את הדור? eimasai yamusu shnei zkeinim halalu v'ani v'atah
nanhig es hador? Ah,
if only these two old people would just kick the bucket and
then we could be the leaders of the generation between me and
you. אמר להן הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lahen Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so
God said to them, נראה מי קובר את מי, nireh mi kover
es mi, let's see who will bury whom. Okay. אמר רב פפא,
amar Rav Pappa, היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi, that's what people
say. נפישי גמלי סבי דטעיני משכי דחוגני. nefishei gamli sabei d'teini mashkei
d'huganei.
There are many old camels that are carrying on their backs the
skins of young camels. Okay. So don't think
that the old ones are going to die and the young ones
are going to take over, especially רש"י Rashi says young camel maybe
has a little bit too much energy and it's too reckless and
it gets itself involved in things and it dies at a young
age. Okay. So anyway, so that's a little background to why נדב
Nadav and אביהוא Avihu died. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar,
moving on. למה תלמיד חכם דומה? l'mah talmid chacham domeh? Now we're
going to discuss a little bit about קרח. Korach. Remember we said
that he gave them all these feasts and he seduced them? So
רש"י Rashi says the assumption is that the עדת קרח, Adas Korach,
it says, קרואי עדה אנשי שם, kru'ei eidah anshei shem, קרואי עדה
נשיאי עדה קריאי מועד אנשי שם. kru'ei eidah nesiei eidah kriei moed
anshei shem. They
were all important people, so then we're going to sort of assume
that means they were all תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Okay. And now
we're going to sort of speak about how he was able to
seduce them but also felt that he was in a position to
manipulate them. למה תלמיד חכם דומה לפני עם הארץ? l'mah talmid chacham
domeh lifnei am ha'aretz? How does a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham appear
to an עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? בתחילה דומה לקיתון של זהב, b'tchilah
domeh l'kiton shel zahav,
originally it appears like a ladle or a pitcher of gold, like
something that's totally holy and off limits and beyond that person, and
therefore they show a lot of respect. סיפר הימנו, siper heimenu, but
if you start schmoozing with them, you feel a little too comfortable,
right? Here's sometimes, here's a point, there's always this challenge about the
rabbi? You don't want your rabbis arrogant and self-centered, but you want
them to hold themselves, right? You want to see your rabbis going
to the supermarket in their shorts or something like that? So if
you start becoming a little bit too familiar, סיפר הימנו דומה לקיתון
של כסף. siper heimenu domeh l'kiton shel kesef. Hey, he's not so
important. It's no longer gold, it's silver. נהנה הימנו, nehenah heimenu, now
if you actually get the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham gets benefit from
the עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, the עם הארץ am ha'aretz lends him
some money, invites him to his house for a שבת lunch, so
now you're just a total pal, nothing special at all. You're even
somebody who I gave
a favor from me. So in that case, דומה לקיתון של חרס.
domeh l'kiton shel cheres. Now he's just like a pitcher of pottery.
כיון שנשבר, keivan shenishbar, and a pottery pitcher once it breaks, שוב
אין לו תקנה, shuv ein lo takanah, it cannot be fixed. So
now that you've gotten to be so familiar, now if you make
some misstep or whatever, you'll never be able to reestablish like your
status and position. So that's like a tricky message, right, you know,
about like how do you, obviously, you know, I think a lot
of us experience sometimes that, you know, rabbis or certain figures hold
themselves too aloft, and then that's not only a problem about arrogance
or whatever and inability to relate, but also leads to other problems.
Anyway, but, you know, but there's also problem about being too familiar.
So the message here anyway was, was that by קרח Korach inviting
all of these esteemed people to his meal, and then being his
beneficiaries, and, you know, and eating from his food or whatever, that
made him feel like, you know, not only did it seduce them,
but it made him feel more that he could manipulate them, and
he was in a position to manipulate them. Okay, anyway, let's finish
up, let's get to the משנה. Mishnah.
אמרתא בת טלי, Imrasa Bas Tali, this woman, אמרתא בת טלי, Imrasa
the daughter of Tali, בת כהן, she was a בת כהן שזינתה.
Bas Kohen shezinisah. אכפסה Akphsah רב חמה בר טוביה Rav Chama bar
Tuvia חבילי זמורות. chavilei zemoros.
So right the משנה, Mishnah. he did this. He not what הלכה
halacha בית דין beis din and, and this by the way, this
רב חמה Rav Chama was lived in the אמוראים Amoraic period after
you can no longer do court executions, but he took it into
his own hands. He wrapped her up with these, you know, these
twigs, a bundle of twigs, ושרפה, vesarfah, and burnt her alive. So
אמר רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef טעה בתרתי. ta be-tarti. He made
two mistakes. טעה בדרב מתנא. ta bedirav Masna. First of all, the
mistake of רב מתנא Rav Masna who says that you don't burn
on the outside, you pour the lead down. It's actually not just
רב מתנא, Rav Masna, it's actually the משנה. Mishnah. רב מתנא Rav
Masna just explained the משנה. Mishnah, וטעה בדתניא ve-ta bedetanya like we
taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. ובאת אל הכהנים הלוים ואל השופט אשר
יהיה בימים ההם. uvasa el hakohanim haleviyim veel hashoftim asher yiheyeh bayamim
hahem. בזמן שיש כהן bizman sheyesh Kohen
when there's a כהן, when there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, and
when the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is situated in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash.
then יש משפט, yesh mishpat, then there's full judgment, then you can
do the death penalties. בזמן שאין כהן bizman she-ain Kohen when there's
no בית המקדש and no סנהדרין Sanhedrin in the בית המקדש, אין
משפט ain mishpat you cannot do the death penalties. Okay, but again
here, I mean, it's first of all very sad because again when
these types where that idea, I mean the whole thing, right, I
mean, look, death penalty is never pleasant. How we do the death
penalty now, you know, you got the electric chair, is it with,
you know, with chemicals or whatever, but still, burning somebody, wrapping somebody
in, you know, wood and burning them alive seems particularly horrific, and
doing it, you know, outside of the formal מיתות בית דין. misos
beis din. As I said, this has always been a case, you
know, throughout Jewish history. You had שמעון בן שטח, you know, you
had in the Middle Ages that they would sometimes take it into
their hands to execute people because it was needed for the sake
of the community, but it wasn't because these were the מיתות in
the תורה and מיתות בית דין. misos beis din, It wasn't for
every sin that you were חייב מיתה for. It was like extra,
you know, judicial, extra-legal types of powers that were being used. So,
but anyway, it's very interesting and sad I think, you know, just
to read such a case. Okay, let's just do now following that
the statement in the משנה. אמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק מעשה בבת
כהן שזינתה. Amar Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok maaseh bevas kohen shezinisah. רבי
אלעזר בר צדוק Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok said I also basically also
saw a case like that. I mean he, he was in a
time when there was מיתות בית דין, misos beis din, and they
said back to me they didn't know what they were
doing. So אמר רב יוסף בית דין של צדוקים הוה. amar Rav
Yosef beis din shel tzedukim havay. Not only did they not know
what they were doing, they were צדוקים, Tzedukim, they were literalists. So
that's why they read the פסוק to mean literally burning in fire.
הכי אמר להו והכי אהדרו להו? hachi amar lehu vehachi ahadru lehu?
So the גמרא says now is really this what happened? רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says this is what I saw and they responded back
they didn't know what they were
doing? והתניא ve-hatanya we taught in a ברייתא Baraisa we heard of
a different exchange. So אמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק amar Rabbi Elazar
bar Tzadok or אלעזר בר צדוק Elazar bar Tzadok said זכורני zechurani
I remember כשהייתי תינוק keshehayisi tinok when I was a child ומורכב
על כתיפו של אבא umorkav al keseyfo shel abba and I was
on my father's shoulders, they brought בת כהן שזינתה, bas kohen shezinisah,
always this poor בת כהן that committed adultery, והקיפוה חבילי זמורות ושרפוה
ve-hikifu chavilei zemoros ve-sarfu
and they burnt her. אמרו לו קטן היית ואין מביאין ראיה מן
הקטן. amru lo katan hayisa ve-ein mevi-in raayah min hakatan.
Yeah, you were a minor, we can't trust anything you say about
the time you were a minor, which is interesting, it's not like
עדות eidus in a court, right, this is like about learning out
what the הלכה practice had been, and even so they dismiss it
because you were a minor. Okay, so now the גמרא says so
that's a different version than the משנה. So the גמרא says שני
מעשיות הוו. shenai maasiyos havay. Fine, there were two stories. He saw
one as a minor and that was dismissed because he was a
minor, and he saw one as an adult and they dismissed that
because they said, you know, the בית דין didn't know what it
was doing. Okay, so הי אמר להו ברישא? hai amar lehu bereisha?
Which of these two stories did he first say to them? אילימא
הא קמייתא, iy-leima ha-kamaisa, the one in our משנה, the one he
saw when he was an adult, אמר להו ברישא amar lehu bereisha
he said that
first. אמר להו כשהוא גדול ולא אשגחו ביה amar lehu keshahu gadol
velo ashgach beih if that, could it be that he told a
story that he saw as an adult and they dismissed it and
they rejected it, then
אמר להו כשהוא קטן? amar lehu keshahu katan? Then he thinks he's
gonna prove something by telling a story that he saw as a
kid? ואשגחו ביה? ve-ashgach beih? He thinks that they'll listen to that?
So couldn't be that was the order. If they dismissed the story
of the adult, he wouldn't have mentioned the story of when he
was a kid. אלא אמר להו ברישא, ella amar lehu bereisha, first
he told them the story of having been a kid, and אמרו
לו קטן היית, amru lo katan hayisa, they dismissed that because they
said he was a kid. ואמר להו כשהוא גדול, va-amar lehu keshahu
gadol, then he said but I saw a case like this when
I was an adult, ואמרו ליה מפני שלא היה בית דין של
אותה שעה בקי, va-amru leh mipnei shelo hayah beis din shel osah
shaah baki,
they didn't know what they were doing. So they were dismissing all
the evidence, right? But again this gets to the fact, you know,
that actually was the way that's being described in this פרק an
accurate historical report of what happened? It seems like it might not
have been. Now you could say it might not have been because
maybe a lot of the בתי דינים Battei Dinim were run by
the צדוקים. Tzadukim. The צדוקים Tzadukim had a lot of the political
and religious power in the time of the בית המקדש. So maybe
that's, you know, you could claim that if, you know, that's why,
you know, maybe this wasn't a single case. But nevertheless it is
interesting, this divergence between, you know, what the הלכה is, what was
practiced in the past when they were doing מיתות בית דין, misos
beis din, how did they do it? And what was practiced throughout
history when it wasn't a formal מיתות בית דין, but when they
actually sometimes did execute people, which wasn't even trying to really follow,
you know, this type of a model. Okay, we'll end with this
for now.